All at the difference, in this video, let's have a look at how do we sort
collections in Java and there are such great ways to do that as you'll come to
see shortly. So we start with the basics again and I mean I'll just use a list
here. Let's say we're just sorting for example the list of strings. We want to do
that. Let's really have a list, a list of names and you see this is an
error list, but you can just go ahead and do it with a link list if you want,
right? I'll say list of names and let's say it's certain strings here so that we
have some data to play around with again as you always see, say some names
let's put this to any, and I don't, okay. So this is good. And obviously you know
that the examples that we've taken until now that this would maintain the
insertion order that is whack would be inserted first, then Snayla and at
last wrong, right? So and you can just edit it out and say list before sorting,
let's put it on the second line and I'll just say list of names. Now if you want
to sort it, there is a way you can sort it out of the box, the default behavior,
all you have to do is you'll say there's a utility class that is collections,
not the collections we are talking about, it's a class in the java.util path.
He's right. I'll say collections dot the static method sort. Why did I say static?
Because I never needed to create an object of collections to call sort directly
with the types of type name dot sort and just pass in the list you want to sort.
That's it. It's such easy. This would sort your list in natural ordering, right?
So this time, out of the box in error list, you know that it's unordered, sorry,
it's ordered in in session order, it's ordered, but unsorted, but this time
this will be sorted in natural order and I can just say let's print the same
thing. After list of the sorting, as you will see, this will be sorted any
would come at the top. Let's go ahead and run this and just check for yourself.
See, this before sorting in the order that you inserted wax me her step
any run and the list out the sorting, right? On chronological order, any
runs me her step and her class to act has been sorted in the most convenient
of manners. Now, taking this example forward, what happens if you want to sort
a custom class object? Obviously, this would work for strings, integers, doubles,
but there's a custom class object, right? And that is, I'll just clear that
I'll say for example, that is a class, let's call it a stick example of that
class, right? And let's make it a Java being and you know now how do we create a
Java being, right? So private instance variables, I'll say private in to, let's
say, yeah, import a property private in SSD or hard drive, for example, for
that matter. And for now, private string, manufacture, right? And let's have one
more property private string name of the laptop and let's quickly go ahead and
create the get a sectors what are required for making this adhere to the
convention of Java means. I'll say get a set for all of them done and I
'll also create a constructor. Okay, I'll just like none, constructors done,
get a set of ready, private instance variables, that's fine. And I can
optionally create a constructor using fields as well, that is for all of them
because if I want to initialize the value of this class at the time I create
an object, that's a generate a constructor for all, which has the RAM, SSD,
manufacturer and stream name. So just with a few clicks, it's all done, right? The
Java being is ready. And now I want to create a list of laptops. For now, I'll
just come in this code. Okay, and I'll just go ahead, I don't say list. Let's create
a type laptop. A laptop only list, that means it can hold any object that is a
type laptop. And I'll just call laptops appropriate, and then select an analyst. My
default again, insertion order. So what you'll do is the laptops, don't edit. I'll
just create a new. All right, and let's put in the values. I need the RAM, SSD
manufacturer, and mean, I'll say RAM is a GB, and I have to put in SSD, let's say 128 GB, let's
say the manufacturer and name. I'll say this is from a Lenovo. And then let's make
it a good example. And I'll say the name is, let's say L, put it free. Yeah. Okay,
let's copy this review times. Let's say three options. Again, new laptop
object can be put to this laptops only list. Why? Because I've defined the
generic parameter of type laptop. Right. Now let's say this is 16 GB SSD, same
Lenovo, the manufacturer L23. And then there is only two. This is two, three, six
GB manufacturer. It's Apple. And this is the MacBook Air. Right. So three laptops
now in this laptops only list. Let's say what the warning says, contents of
collection laptops are updated, but never query. To signal this warning for
now, it does have no repercussions. Right. It will just take care of that in a
moment. Now, if you, in this out, that's a sound, and you just see laptops, see
what it gets us. See, and this is laptop objects, but these hacks that
they're similar, you don't know which object is what, right? You know, in the
previous video, I've talked about two string overriding two string. So that
is why we would need, we would need to, or I do string here as well, because
you want to get meaningful information with these laptops, right? So what I
do is, I just have a version of two string. Again, I'll ask my ID that is
intelligent to generate that for me. I'll say two string and include all the
properties. So that I know which laptop that is. And now immediately when you run
this two string, as you know, from a one of the videos on two string, that it's
it's implicitly called. Now, you should get the insertion on the scene. Select
up, that is, ramid 128 manufacturer, Leno, name is L23, which was
introduced, insert it first. Then the 16 GB one Leno again, and then the last one
Apple, the MacBook L. Okay. So that is what we saw how it came in. Now, you want to
sort it. So I'll say again, collections, but sort. And this time, I'll pass it
now, laptop list, but now what worked earlier, like this here, same. This perfectly
worked here, doesn't work here. The same logic, the same code error. Why you
hover on this? It says that required list t provided list laptop, it says
these are no instance of type t exists, so that laptop confronts to
comparable, just remember that. So turns out, how did this worked earlier,
collections were sort when I passed in a list, which was of type string, right,
because turns out string implements an interface in Java called
comparable, right. And for this collections to sort to work, you can only
pass in an argument of a type list, which has implemented, compare again, I
just rephrase it for you to make it better understandable and clear. That
is collections to sort takes a parameter of a list, in which you store objects
of a type of a class, which is implemented, comparable, and turns out string
behind the scenes implements comparable, integer, does that all the
important wrapper classes, all the important and the wrapper classes implement
comparable, that's why it works. And your laptop class, because it's a laptop
only list, it does not implement comparable. And why do we have to
implement, and why do those classes implement comparable to make sorting like a
piece of cake look, work like a piece of cake, that is, inside the, whenever
you try to sort your collection, right, you should define your logic, how does
it know, do I sort it on the basis of RAM, or on the basis of SSD, or on the
basis of manufacture, or name, how does it know, how do you expect it to sort it
right. And how do you expect this to be sorted, because the logic is written
behind the scenes in the string class, when they have implemented comparable, and
over written one of its methods, because comparable has just one maker
behind the scene, and that is compared to. And your class should override that, and
write the logic there for your, for your sorting to take place later on. So I do
that as a class laptop, say implements, not bad. This one, Java to Clank. I told
you some of the interfaces, this is an interface comparable, it is a Java to
like, not in Java due to, right. And now you hover on this, it's an error by,
because you know the rules that is interface methods need to be overrated in
the subclasses, or the subclass also needs to be declared as abstract, I don't
want to do that, I want to implement that. So how on that say implement methods,
just one maker compare to, and it takes an object, takes an object, right. So
public and compare to object O return zero, right. And this method is called
automatically, when you call sort behind the scene, recursually. And if the left
hand side object is greater than right hand side, it returns a value in minus. If
they're equal zero, if it is greater, it returns a value plus. So all you have to do
is define your logic. All right. So what I'll do is, I'll say return, right, and I'll
say return this dot, get, let's see, I decide to sort them on the basis of the
RAM, let's say get RAM, now what does get RAM return? It returns an int, right. So
I need an integer, because only then I can call the dot operator, right. So
better is what I do is I just change it here to integer, the wrapper class integer,
and then what I'll do is, I'll say return this dot this, this dot get RAM dot compare to,
I'll say O dot, again, get RAM is not an object, it won't be called, you need a type
of cost here, now that's like this. Teacher, that's how you do the reference variable type
casting, you know that, and we do it, what does it say, return this or get RAM, returns an integer, got
them get to, we converted this O into an integer, this was done here, this is dot RAM is
for a moment to just, we converted this into an integer just a moment, and then we should say
get some but, okay sorry, my, my bad, not integer, laptop, and now this will work,
because get RAM is in laptop dot integer, and to avoid such painful convergence and not unsafe
operations, because this can give you a class class exception at RAM time, because if you pass any
other object that's not a laptop, so to avoid that, what we can do is, we can put in the generic
argument for compareable here, see the benefits of compareable, I'll say please do this for laptops,
right, and now when you do this, this becomes a laptop, they're not an object,
and now you do not need the cost, I'm going to step this, absolutely, right, we do not need the
type casting to be put in here, right, but this is how you put the logic for sorting your list
inside compare to, which would be called automatically, once you call collections dot sort,
and do you see this, the same language was giving an error is not anymore, why, because your
past a parameter of the right type, what is that, that is collections dot sort, takes one on
human of a list in which you've stored objects of a type, which has implemented comparable,
and R type now has implemented comparable, it has the logic, how do I want them to be sorted on the
basis of RAM, and we go ahead and bring them afterwards, let's say system product of print Ln,
up to sorting list looks like this, I call it laptops, it will be sorted in natural ordering
by their who are around this, say laptop RAM first RAM 8, then 16, then 32, right, but you might
wonder that we put it in that same order, right, so that is just by by incident, but let's try
to reverse order them, you can do that as well, all you have to do is just change the order of this
and oh, let's say over here, let's say this here, and now run this, you would see like a sorting
logic is fact working C plus 32, the laptops for the RAM 32 on the higher end, then 16, then the
last one laptop with the RAM 8 has been ordered has been sorted in reverse natural ordering,
right, so that's the logic of collections or sort using comparable now, if you decide to sort them
on the basis of their let's say name, you can even do that, all you have to do is just say
get name, and I don't want to do reverse sort and this say O dot get name, just change it right here,
let's see your logic, right, and run this, you don't need to change it at the top, see now first,
the Apple one should come doesn't come, that means something wrong here, let's see what did I get
wrong, I said this or get name or compare to O dot get name, and I printed it out, oh sorry,
I put the name wrong here, right, this is Apple, I want to sort them on the basis of manufacturer,
right, that's right, see the Apple one's because A is at the start and then Leno and Leno,
right, so this was sorted by their manufacturer, so whenever you want to change it, you have to
go ahead and change it here, that brings me to the disadvantage of comparable, if you want to sort
your collections with comparable, it's one dimension, why there are few disadvantages, the first
disadvantages you have to actually think of the code within your class entity class, you have to
write the logic for comparing for sorting in the laptop class, right, that's never a good,
good programming practice, why, objectory to design philosophy says our classes should be highly
cohesive, what does that mean, one task, one goal per class, there should just be one task per class,
but you are now diluting that, you're writing the laptop specific things here as well as sorting
them, right, the logic for sorting them, the second disadvantage is whenever you have to change things,
that is you want to sort of the base of name, you know, you have to go ahead and change it in the
actual code in the laptop class, and then change it here as well, right, so two glaring
disadvantages, although this works, but it's not a good programming practice, it's not recommended,
that's why we move on to the second way, my personal favorite way, and that's what the industry
uses as well, to sort collections in Java, and that is using comparator, and we talk about
comparator in the next video.